Guide to the South Africa documentary photographs collection, 1940s-circa 2013, bulk 1960s-2013 RL.01129
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Then and Now: Eight South African Photographers, 1963-2006, 160 prints
  - Graeme Williams, Then, 1987-2006, 6 prints (Box 26)
    Images during the earlier period, in color as well as black-and-white, show a crowd clashing with police, an Inkatha member killed during a protest march, Archibishop Tutu calming a crowd, white re-enactors during the Day of the Vow celebrations at the Voortrekker Monument, Pretoria, a patient in an AIDS clinic, and other urban scenes. Later images in black-and-white and color document life for white and black residents of urban Johannesburg and South African townships; some of the color images tend to a more abstract design.
    Other images by Williams can be found in the Underexposed series.
  - Graeme Williams, Then / Now, 1987-2006, 14 prints (Box 27)
  - Gisèle Wulfsohn, Then / Now, 1984-2005, 13 prints (Box 28)
    Wulfsohn's images from the apartheid era are mostly in color, and focus on affluent South Africans and their relationship with other communities; images show a polling station during democratic elections of 1994, domestics at work, and fashion designers at a photo shoot. Her post-apartheid images in this series feature black-and-white portraits of women activists Maniben Sita and Ellen Khuzwayo, and HIV positive men, women and children at home and in clinics. Other images by Wulfsohn can be found in the Underexposed series.
  - Gisèle Wulfsohn, Now, 1984-2005, 7 prints (Box 29)
  - Exhibit opening audio file, 120 MB
    Audio mp3 file recording the opening event for the "Then and Now" exhibit at Duke University, with speakers and musicians. The file has been mounted to the library server; please consult with a reference archivist for access. It is also available through the home page of the online Duke University Libraries exhibit.
- Underexposed, 1940s-2007 and undated, 656 prints
  These images by relatively unknown and "underexposed" South African photographers were collected as part of a project sponsored by the Centre for Curating the Archive at the University of Cape Town and photographer/curator Paul Weinberg. The photographs feature a variety of subjects, including South African political protests, family life, leisure pursuits, rural life, poverty, and work life. Some of the images were taken during the 1940s and 1950s - a significant glimpse into South African society and culture at the time.
  The "Underexposed" series houses over 600 color and black-and-white prints. There are approximately 50 digital prints from each photographer, as well as a smaller number of vintage gelatin silver prints. Digital prints are 11.5x16.5 inch pigmented inkjet prints on Epson Archival Matte Paper.
  Eleven photographers are represented: Rodney Barnett, Arthur Bolton, Basil Breakey, Anne Fischer, Jenny Gordon, David Hemson, Daniel Morolong, Cedric Nunn, Graeme Williams, Janje Wissema, and Gisèle Wulfsohn. The work of some of these photographers is also found in other series in this collection. Prints are grouped by photographer. The 151 prints that comprise the output of one photographer, Graeme Williams, are arranged in six topical subseries, and appear first. All other photographers are listed in alphabetical order.
  - Graeme Williams, 1989-2007, 151 prints
    There are six bodies of work arranged in alphabetical order; titles were assigned by the photographer. Four of the projects consist of gelatin silver (black-and-white) prints: Hlabisa AIDS Orphans, Interplays, Sacred Heart House, and Two Dogs. In addition, there are two series of color prints entitled Hard Ground and The Edge of Town. Each body of work is described fully in its subseries entry.
    Images from The Edge of Town are also available on the library server as digital files. Please contact the Rubenstein Library's Research Services Department for access to these files.
    A few images from Graeme William's projects in this series are also found in the Then and Now series in this collection.
    - The Edge of Town, color reference prints, 2004-2007, 22 prints (Box 30)
      The subseries consists of 22 5x7 inch color reference prints, and 48 8x10 inch color original prints. Images often resemble collages, with the camera capturing individuals and street scenes in the poor and disenfranchised areas of cities and townships, along with fragments of public artwork, graffiti, signs, and street advertisements. Box of 8x10 prints includes a photographer's statement essay on the project and a CD-ROM with image files.
    - The Edge of Town, 8x10 inch color prints, 2004-2007, 48 prints; one-page essay; one CD-R; About half of the prints bear labels on the backs, with titles, dates, and locations. (Box 31)
    - Hard Ground, 8x10 inch color inkjet prints, 2003, 22 prints (Box 32)
      Consists of 8.25 x 8.5 inch color portraits of mine workers posed individually or in groups in their work environments. Although they are mostly black men, there are also white workers as well as one woman. Comes with a photographer's statement and an inventory of images and titles. The images were commissioned by the University of Cape Town for an exhibit in the University's Chemical Engineering Building.
    - Hlabisa AIDS Orphans, 8x10 inch gelatin silver prints, 2001, 19 prints - 18 unique images (Box 33)
      Series consists of 8x10 inch gelatin silver portraits of children, many of them HIV-positive, orphaned by the AIDS epidemic, taken by Graeme Williams in Hlabisa, KwaZulu-Natal, South Africa. In many of the images, adult caretakers or relatives are pictured with the children. Settings are both inside and outside clinics and village homes. One print has an additional copy. From the photographer's online statement: "The portraits were taken in the Hlabisa District of KwaZulu-Natal in conjunction with Cotlands and its Home Based Care Project (Cotlands is a nationwide organisation caring for Aids orphans). Hlabisa has an abnormally high percentage of people suffering from HIV/Aids."
    - Interplays, 8x10 inch gelatin silver prints, 1989-1997, 18 prints (Box 34)
      These 8x10 inch gelatin silver prints portray the daily life of and interactions between members of a Johannesburg communal household that included photographer Graeme Williams. Subjects include outdoor recreation, marriage and baptism, relationships between couples, parents and children, nudes, and scenes of life at home. A list of captions and a photographer's statement taken from the photographer's website is housed with the photographs.
    - Sacred Heart House, 8x10 inch gelatin silver prints, circa 1991, 11 prints (Box 35)
      Series consists of 8x10 inch gelatin silver portraits of staff, patients, and volunteers at a Catholic AIDS hospice in Kensington, Johannesburg. Sister Cecelia is among the staff; one image also shows a dying man with his sister. A few images were taken out of doors but most are interior shots.
    - Two Dogs, 8x10 inch gelatin silver prints, 1999-2000, 11 prints (Box 36)
      A series of 8x10 inch gelatin silver action shots of two black dogs playing with athletic abandon on a beach at Pringle Bay near Cape Town.
  - Rodney Barnett, 50 prints
    Chiefly comprises portraits of South African men, women, and children in rural and urban settings; locations include Lesotho, Botswana, Cape Town, and Johannesburg. Other portraits are of individuals and groups in Greece, England, Peru, and Turkey. Scenes include people in the street, religious festivals and rites, herders, children playing, and family groups.
    - Black-and-white 11.75x16.5 inch pigmented inkjet prints (Box 37)
  - Arthur Bolton, 50 prints
    The bulk consists of formal portraits from about the 1940s to the 1960s of men, women, and children, almost all Zulu in tribal dress; most are commissioned studio portraits of couples, often with the man in Western dress, and individuals. Some were taken in outdoor settings and are portraits of young Zulu girls and women, and Westerners posing with Zulus. Also includes a group of photographs from the same period depicting members of Bolton's family.
    - Black-and-white 11.75x16.5 inch pigmented inkjet prints (Box 38)
  - Basil Breakey, 47 prints
    Photographs in the subseries show South African jazz musicians, vocalists, bands, audiences, instruments, and other jazz-related themes.
    - Black-and-white 11.75x16.5 inch pigmented inkjet prints (Box 39)
  - Anne Fischer, 53 prints
    These prints are almost all portraits of black and mixed-race individuals, chiefly residing in the Transkei (Xhosa people), Basutoland, and the settlement of Genadendal in the Western Cape. The photographs are undated but were taken sometime during the 1950s-1970s. The photographer focused especially on the elderly, children, and laborers.
    - Black-and-white 11.75x16.5 inch pigmented inkjet prints (Box 40)
  - Jenny Gordon, 57 prints
    Arranged into three projects with titles assigned by the photographer: Breathing Spaces, which focuses on portraits of people living in an industrial zone of Durban; the Mai Mai Project, images of residents of a migrant hostel in Johannesburg; and Johannesburg Portraits, images of families and individuals, young and old, living in inner city suburbs such as Hillbrow. All prints measure 11.75x16.5 inches and are black-and-white pigmented inkjet.
    - Breathing Spaces: Environmental Portraits of Durban's Industrial South, black-and-white 11.75x16.5 pigmented inkjet prints, 2002-2007, 19 prints (Box 41)
      The subseries consists of black-and-white portraits of men, women and children primarily at homes in Merewent, Durban.
    - Mai Mai Project, black-and-white 11.75x16.5 pigmented inkjet prints, 19 prints (Box 41)
      Consists of portraits of men and women in and around the Mai Mai migrant worker hostel in Johannesburg.
    - Johannesburg Portraits, black-and-white 11.75x16.5 pigmented inkjet prints, 1980s, 19 prints (Box 41)
      Portraits in Hillbrow and other Johannesburg inner city suburbs. Subjects are primarily portrayed at home.
  - David Hemson, 41 prints
    Hemson's images center on political protests, especially anti-apartheid marches, populated by soldiers, protesters, political leaders, and spectators. There are also photographs of cranes, equipment, and workers in industrial settings, including the shipping port of Durban.
    - Black-and-white 11.75x16.5 inch pigmented inkjet prints (Box 42)
  - Daniel Morolong, 1940s-1960s, 48 prints
    These early black-and-white and color images depict posed groups or informally gathered groups of black South Africans, especially at social clubs and other event locations. There are also multiple portraits of black athletes, chiefly boxers. There are many photographs of Morolong's family at home, at the beach, and elsewhere. Prints were produced in the 1980s.
    - Color and black-and-white 11.75x16.5 inch pigmented inkjet prints (Box 43)
  - Cedric Nunn, 59 prints
    The settings for these prints are mainly in rural South Africa and impoverished urban areas, and include locales in Durban, Arniston, and Magopa. Many of the images are portraits of elderly people, laborers, women and men, children, migrants, and squatters; there are also a few of political party activists. There are also a handful of images taken in Angola, chiefly of the effects of war in that country. The series includes six vintage prints from the 1980s in sizes varying from 8x10 to 16x20 inches.
    Other images by Nunn can be found in the Beyond the Barricades, Cordoned Heart, and Then and Now series.
    - Color and black-and-white 11.75x16.5 inch pigmented inkjet prints, 53 prints (Box 44)
    - 8x10 inch gelatin silver vintage prints, 1980s, 2 prints (Box 36)
    - 12x16 and 16x20 inch gelatin silver vintage prints, 1980s, 4 prints (Box 45)
  - Jansje Wissema, 50 prints
    Chiefly portraits of children and adults of various ethnicities and religions on the street and at home in Cape Town's District Six. There are also photographs of buildings such as shanties, apartment houses, bungalows, stores, and churches, as well as images of demolished structures.
    - Black-and-white 11.75x16.5 inch pigmented inkjet prints (Box 46)
      - Unidentified prints, 3 prints
        Photographs whose photographer has not been identified depict a black protester speaking at a rally or meeting, a white woman and toddler with a black servant, and an older black person in a poorly furnished dwelling with two toddlers.
        - Black-and-white 11x16 prints (Box 47)
  - Gisèle Wulfsohn, 50 prints
    Comprises two main bodies of work: one on South African individuals affected by or openly living with HIV/AIDS, and a 2006 series of portraits of female South African activists, including Amina Cachalia, Thandi Modise, Geina Mhlophe, Phyllis Naidoo, Bettie du Toit, Helen Suzman, Jean Sinclair, Adelaide Frances (Tshukudu) Tambo, and Ray Alexander Simons. Other images by Wulfsohn can be found in the Then and Now series.
    - Color and black-and-white 11.75x16.5 inch pigmented inkjet prints (Box 47)
- The Other Camera, circa 1970-circa 2013; 25 prints 1 box 13x19 inches
  These 25 black-and-white and color photographic prints form part of "The Other Camera" project and exhibit, curated by Paul Weinberg, and offer a view of the many different styles and approaches of 20th century South African street photography. The images were taken by male and female photographers from the 1970s through the 2010s, and were produced in inkjet format by Weinberg, then archived, digitized, and exhibited with support from the University of Cape Town and Duke University. These images are a selection of prints from the exhibit; all of the images are available through the online e-book, The Other Camera (2014).
  The known artists represented in this collection are: Lucky Sipho Khoza (3 prints); William Matlala (5); Lindeka Qampi (10); and one print by Paul Weinberg. There are also six prints from the work of an unknown photographer from Maribastad, Gauteng Province (near Pretoria), from the collection of photographer and film-maker Angus Gibson.
  All of the images are portraits of black South Africans, men and women. Themes include street culture, township life, the individual gaze, human identity and status, South African families, and social conditions in South Africa.
  The images are all inkjet prints measuring 13x19 inches, and were exhibited at Duke University in 2014.
  Biographical Note
  Paul Weinberg, exhibit and project coordinator, is a photographer and Senior Curator of the Visual Archives, University of Capetown Libraries, Capetown, South Africa.
  Note on Use
  Inkjet prints are extremely vulnerable to moisture and contaminants. Please use gloves when handling these prints.
  - Angus Gibson Collection prints by unknown photographer, circa 1970, 6 prints (Box 48)
    Taken by an unknown photographer sometime around 1970, these images are black-and-white studio portraits of men and women. They include a man in uniform, a man with a degree and graduation robes, a single woman, two musicians with a guitar and trumpet, and a man with two small children, one of whom appears to be albinistic.
    The prints have all been given the same title of "Unknown photographer, studio portrait, Marabastad, Gauteng." Marabastad is a historic district near Pretoria; Gauteng is its province.
    These are among the few surviving prints from this studio; they were created from negatives by Angus Gibson, who later returned to the location to find that the studio was gone and the negatives had been destroyed.
  - Lucky Sipho Khoza, circa 1999, 3 prints (Box 48)
    These color photographs are examples of a popular genre whereby portraits are superimposed on an artificial and sometimes incongruous backgound, such as the print showing a woman's face on a large Coca-Cola aluminium can.
  - William Matlala, 1990s, 5 prints (Box 48)
    Matlala's color portraits of men and women are relaxed and casual, showing individuals and sometimes pairs of black South Africans outside and in their houses. There is one print of a wedding street celebration.
  - Lindeka Qampi, circa 2008-2013, 10 prints (Box 48)
    Chiefly focusing on portraits of black South African women, these ten images are the only ones in this series by a female photographer, and are the most recently created. They abound with saturated color, and are all taken on the street or in some outside setting.
  - Paul Weinberg, "'Take me a photo', Durban beach, KwaZulu-Natal," 1995, 1 prints (Box 48)
    This single color print by Weinberg, the curator of the exhibit "The Other Camera," portrays a South African photographer at work on a Cape Town beach, and was used as a framing piece for the exhibit's theme of street photography in South Africa.
- Jeeva Rajgopaul Photographs, 1980s-1990s; 10 prints 1 box
  These prints by photographer Jeeva Rajgopaul were received along with the South Africa Documentary Photography collection. The 10 black-and-white portraits of South African men and women are untitled and undated, but were likely taken during the 1980s and 1990s. They measure approximately 11x14 inches. The individuals are unidentified but are likely to be chiefly activists, writers, and artists.
  - Black-and-white prints, circa 1980s-1990s, 10 prints (Box 49)